Butcher, Joan; Papers apap410
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Joan Butcher Papers
1973-2020
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap410
.99 cubic ft.
This collection contains material related to Joan Butcher's lesbian and feminist activism and other work in New York State and the Capital Region.
Biographical Note
Joan Butcher, born October 1943 in New York, came to her full lesbian, feminist activism after teaching for years in public and special education schools, including teaching students with learning disabilities. During a brief stint as a paralegal assistant with a New York City law firm, she began attending Westchester National Organization for Women (NOW) chapter meetings and joined a consciousness raising group. The slow progress for approval of the Federal Equal Rights Amendment; as well as multiple injustices towards women, LGBTQ and other disenfranchised communities made her decide in her late thirties to devote the rest of her work life to fighting injustice.
She moved to Albany to become the NOW-New York State office manager and chair of its lesbian rights task force as well as the office coordinator and member of the board of the Women's Building of Albany. Other employment included public information coordinator and newsletter editor for the New York State Coalition Against Domestic Violence, rural health project coordinator for the StateWide Senior Action Council and project coordinator of the Speakout on Teen Pregnancy.
Butcher was one of the convenors and co-chair of the New York State Lesbian Gay Lobby (a coalition of 40 state and local organizations) and chair of the New York State Human Rights Advisory Council in Albany. Butcher was honored for her work and activism, receiving the following awards: Albany NOW Making Waves, New York State Human Rights Advisory Council and Human Rights Players, and the Harvey Milk for Activism for the LGBTQ community.
Using her gift for music and belief in its power to unite hearts and open minds Butcher also was involved in creating and sharing local fame with a variety of youth, elderly, feminist and Unitarian non audition choruses.
Butcher received a BA from Wagner College, Staten Island, in 1967 and her MS from SUNY Potsdam in 1968. Although she was born, raised, educated, and worked in New York State throughout her life, the desire to leave its winter weather caused her to move to Florida in 2010.
Content Description
This colleciton contains subject files; news clippings; correspondence; artifacts, including buttons, magnets, and pins. There are materials documenting Joan Butcher's lesbian and feminist activism and other work in New York State and the Captial Region including the National Organization for Women (NOW) New York State and Albany chapters, the Women's Building, the Capital District Lesbian and Gay Community Center, and the New York StateWide Senior Action Council.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Joan Butcher donated all items in this collection in 2023.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is arranged alphabetically.
Butcher, Joan; Women's rights -- New York (State); Lesbian activists -- New York (State).; Gay rights--New York (State); Women; Human Sexuality and Gender Identity; Albany (N.Y.) -- Politics and government.; Human rights workers.; Social Activists and Public Advocates
- Activist Buttons, Magnets, Pins, 1983; 1991; 2016; Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- Albany NOW Making Waves Awards, 1986; 1989; 1999; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Black History, 1988; 2014; 2017; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Consciousness Raising, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Domestic Violence Actions, 1981-1982; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Dukakis Campaign, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- ERA Now, 1981; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Historical Magnets, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- Human Rights Activities, 2006; 2019-2020; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Human Rights Quotes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Lesbian Articles, 1977; 1979; 1992; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Lesbian Rights Plan, 1981-1985; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Mondale-Cranston-Ferraro, 1982; 1988; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Music, 1975; 1993; 2006; 2017; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- National Museum of American History and Culture, 2012; 2016; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- New York City Events and Information, 1979; 1983-1985; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- New York State Division of Human Rights Advisory Council Meeting, 1982; 1991; 1993-1994; 2000; Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- New York State Lesbian and Gay Lobby, 1986-1988; 1990; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- New York State Lesbian and Gay Rights, 1979-1986; 1992-1993; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- NOW New Orleans, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- NY Statewide Senior Action Council, 1988-1990; Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Other Employment History, 1973; 1986; 1990; 2002-2003; Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Personal Writing Samples, 1982-1986; 1988; 1990; 1992; 1999-2003 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Photographs, The Women's Building/New York State Coalition Against Domestic Violence, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Political Bumper Stickers, 1985; 2002-2003; 2012; 2016; Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Political Stickers, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Quotes and Humor, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Virginia Apuzzo and Governor Mario Cuomo, 1981-1982; 1985-1986; Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Washington D.C. Marches, 1987; 1993 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Women's Building, 1986; 1988-1989; 1993; Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Women's Rights History and Wisdom, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Youth Speak Out on Teen Pregnancy, 1987-1988; Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)